<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
  
  
  <link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-07-22T10:33:38+00:00</updated>
  <id>//</id>

  
    <title type="html">Bayevels Thoughts</title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Bayevels Thoughts is a blog where I talk about my journey becoming a good enough Software Software developer. Senegal, Software development, Africa, RubyOnRails, VueJS, Typescript, Javascript, Ruby, Rust</subtitle>
  

  

  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Luckily I find a way to build blazing fast Web Apps using Ruby syntax</title>
      
      
      <link href="/2021/05/02/luckyli-a-way-to-build-blazing-fast-web-app-using-ruby-syntax/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Luckily I find a way to build blazing fast Web Apps using Ruby syntax" />
      
      <published>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/2021/05/02/luckyli-a-way-to-build-blazing-fast-web-app-using-ruby-syntax</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/2021/05/02/luckyli-a-way-to-build-blazing-fast-web-app-using-ruby-syntax/">&lt;p&gt;Let me introduce to you &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.luckyframework.org/&quot;&gt;Lucky&lt;/a&gt; a blazing fast web framework written in Crystal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wait, yet another language to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re a Rails developer or you use Ruby regularly, Crystal is a great option to look for when building type checked and blazing fast apps using the Ruby syntax, the learning curve is almost near to 0 for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re not familiar to Ruby, it’s probably one of the most &lt;em&gt;programmer happiness centric&lt;/em&gt; scripting language and reading or writting Ruby code feel generally like reading or writting english. Crystal main aim is to recreate the efficiency and friendliness of the Ruby language in a compiled and typed fashion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We love Ruby’s efficiency for writing code.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We love C’s efficiency for running code.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We want the best of both worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We want the compiler to understand what we mean without having to specify types everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We want full OOP.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Oh, and we don’t want to write C code to make the code run faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;crystal-lang&quot;&gt;Crystal Lang&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crystal&lt;/strong&gt; is a compiled programming language with a syntax similar to &lt;strong&gt;Ruby&lt;/strong&gt; (but compatibility is not a goal). The v1.0.0 was released on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/crystal-lang/crystal/pull/10500&quot;&gt;March 2021&lt;/a&gt;. Crystal has a good community support with more than 16k stars on Github at the time I write this blog. Crystal docs and guides are also really great and concise and you can learn and grasp the language at the speed of light :). Crystal is typically accompanied by &lt;a href=&quot;https://crystal-lang.org/reference/the_shards_command/index.html&quot;&gt;Shards&lt;/a&gt;, its dependency manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;lucky-framework&quot;&gt;Lucky Framework&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucky is a Rails like Framework written in Crystal with a great, clear and concise documentation, according to the TechEmpower web framework benchmarks &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.techempower.com/benchmarks/#section=data-r20&amp;amp;hw=ph&amp;amp;test=json&amp;amp;c=e&quot;&gt;Round 20&lt;/a&gt;, Lucky is one of the fasters framework out there. the key point to notice here is Lucky is not a micro framework it’s a “Full-Stack” frameworks that provide you all the necessary tools to build complete web apps.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/webframeworkbench.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Web Framework Benchmarks&quot; /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.luckyframework.org/guides/handling-files/file-uploads&quot;&gt;Lucky&lt;/a&gt; comes with all the good stuffs like HTTP and Routing, Frontend and HTML, Database, JSON and APIs, Authentication, etc… When it’s come to specific thinks like file attachement you can quickly find a shard that does the work for you. Shards are generally heavily inspired by Ruby gems, this makes then really easy to use when you have experience with the Ruby version. For exemple &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jetrockets/shrine.cr&quot;&gt;shrine.rc&lt;/a&gt; used for file attachment is inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/shrinerb/shrine&quot;&gt;shrinerb&lt;/a&gt;. You can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://crystal.libhunt.com/&quot;&gt;Awesome Crystal&lt;/a&gt; a curated list of awesome Crystal shards, tools and frameworks to find quickly the shard that you’re looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-requests-are-processed&quot;&gt;How requests are processed&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/request-overview-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Requests Overview&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Browser or client makes an HTTP request.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lucky routes the request to a matching Action.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Action processes the request. For example:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Query the database with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.luckyframework.org/guides/database/intro-to-avram-and-orms&quot;&gt;Avram&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Create or update db records with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.luckyframework.org/guides/database/intro-to-avram-and-orms&quot;&gt;Avram&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Send an email with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.luckyframework.org/guides/emails/sending-emails-with-carbon&quot;&gt;Carbon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Action generates a response for the browser or client. For example:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Generate an HTML page.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Redirect to another URL or Action.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Send JSON.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Finally the response is delivered to the browser or client.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;wrap-up&quot;&gt;Wrap Up&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that Lucky is great tool for teams that are already familiar with Ruby using Ruby On Rails or Sinatra and have  of the systems that they maintain. 
To keep this post concise, I have wrote a post where I have builded using Lucky a “car model data” api that return YEAR, Make, Model and Body style of nearly all cars manufactured between 1992 and 2020 approximately 10K car models. I try to explain there in detail how to build APIs using&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;useful-links&quot;&gt;Useful links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.luckyframework.org/&quot;&gt;Lucky&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://crystal-lang.org/&quot;&gt;Crystal Lang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.luckyframework.org/guides/http-and-routing/routing-and-params&quot;&gt;Action&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.luckyframework.org/guides/database/intro-to-avram-and-orms&quot;&gt;Avram&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.luckyframework.org/guides/emails/sending-emails-with-carbon&quot;&gt;Carbon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.to/konung/lucky-is-fast-2gpp&quot;&gt;Lucky is lightning fast!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="WebDev" />
      

      
        <category term="Lucky" />
      
        <category term="Rails Like" />
      
        <category term="Crystal" />
      
        <category term="Software development" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Let me introduce to you Lucky a blazing fast web framework written in Crystal.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Finding tech jobs in Senegal the dilemma. Ep. 0</title>
      
      
      <link href="/2021/04/18/finding-tech-jobs-in-senegal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finding tech jobs in Senegal the dilemma. Ep. 0" />
      
      <published>2021-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/2021/04/18/finding-tech-jobs-in-senegal</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/2021/04/18/finding-tech-jobs-in-senegal/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;software-rules-the-world---its-kingdom-is-growing&quot;&gt;Software Rules the World – &amp;amp; Its Kingdom is Growing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “father of software quality” Watt S. Humphrey said 2 decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Every business is a software business&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was true 2 decades ago in most of the Businesses, they were all using in some way or another softwares to help run their business. In fact any business back then has at least a bank account and we all know that
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/the-whole-world-financial-systems-held-by-excel.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The whole world financial systems held by excel&quot; /&gt; 
The CEO of Microsoft, Satya Nadella, repeats the message&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;all companies are software companies&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software is ubiquitous in every company this days. 2 decades ago software was ruling business in this decade we can say without hesitation that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Software Rules the World – &amp;amp; Its Kingdom is Growing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;software-jobs-rules-the-job-market-shares----their-kingdoms-are-growing&quot;&gt;Software Jobs Rules the Job Market Shares - &amp;amp; Their Kingdoms are Growing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The demand for IT professionals (Developer, Software Engineer, Data Analyst, CyberSecurity Engineer, AR/VR developer,…) is by far higher than the job seekers. According to the Hired 2020 State of Software Engineering report, in the US only the demand for AR/VR talent is 1,400% higher than it was a year ago, while blockchain demand has grown by 517% during that same period. It’s a great time to be a IT guy you can have work with leterally no degree and you can earn higher than average salaries. This is also true for the european job market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;software-jobs-the-state-in-africa&quot;&gt;Software Jobs the state in Africa&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;African’s rides the same wave than their fellows from overseas, the demand for IT professionals is growing really fast and there is lots of compagnies that are becoming IT first. In recent years, companies like &lt;a href=&quot;https://andela.com/&quot;&gt;Andela&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gebeya.com/&quot;&gt;GEBEYA&lt;/a&gt; and many others have emerged, this companies are specialized in recruting, training (if needed) and matching IT professionnal (most of the time developers) with compagnies abroad (generally North American) to fill the gap of workers or with african compagnies where most of the HR people are not trained to recruit IT professionals. There is also lots of big tech compagnies (GAFAA, FAANG of whatever suit you) that are creating IT branch in african countries. Nigeria, Ghana and South Africa are hubs where lots of &lt;strong&gt;Giant&lt;/strong&gt; tech compagnies are hiring really talented young africans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;jekyll-twitter-plugin&quot;&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;🇬🇭 Twitter is now present on the continent.  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Thank you Ghana and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/NAkufoAddo?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@NAkufoAddo&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/TwitterGhana?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#TwitterGhana&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/tt7KR3kvDg&quot;&gt;https://t.co/tt7KR3kvDg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; jack (@jack) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jack/status/1381609431381766147?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 12, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;thought-for-senegal&quot;&gt;Thought for Senegal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://fr.wiktionary.org/wiki/flou&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flou&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Stack Developer living in Senegal, I can definetely tell that there is a huge demand for software developers. Almost every day job offers related to software development are posted on social media, on recruting plateforms like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.emploisenegal.com/&quot;&gt;Emploi Senegal&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.emploidakar.com/&quot;&gt;Emploi Dakar&lt;/a&gt; or shared by word of mouth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the last three, word of mouth is the most dominant one HR people are not trained to hire software engineer, most of the time they don’t even know what to put on the job description, they know that they need someone who can craft software but they can’t make the difference between a web developer and a mobile Application developer, and I’m not even talking about making the difference between a Front End Developer or a Back End one, a Mobile Native Developer and a Hybrid App developer :).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the existence of more job offers than job seekers, it’s really difficult and even sometimes impossible to find a IT job in Senegal whether you’re a developer or a data expert with no experience or a senior level, employers still prefer to use their network and recommendations from friends in order to hire Software developers. The few one who try to post job description go with good intention but end up with really confusing job description.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have suffer from that has a job seeker and &lt;em&gt;I’m still suffering from that&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-dilemma&quot;&gt;The Dilemma&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/dilemma.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The whole world financial systems held by excel&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;« Dilemme » Enfin, de deux choses, l’une mon cher : ou bien votre pharmacie est moderne et ne peut avoir été fondée en 1705 ou bien elle a été réellement fondée à cette époque et ne peut prétendre à être moderne. Je vous enferme dans ce dilemme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demand is high their is lots of seekers but they struggle finding each other and they all operate inside an industry that claim to simplify humans life by giving them access to what they need without effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-solution&quot;&gt;The Solution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to tackle this questions by building a super simple yet super powerful :) plateform that will let job seekers find easily job offers and job offerers create understandable job posts within 2 &lt;strong&gt;WEEKS&lt;/strong&gt; from now (Monday 19th 2021). Called … to be honest I don’t have a name rigth now but I’ll figure it out I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within 2 week ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it possible ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well will know it at the end of the week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already have lots of things going on in my life rigth now but will add that to it :).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m thinking of something similar to &lt;a href=&quot;https://remoteok.io/&quot;&gt;Remote OK&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WISH ME LUCK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;useful-links&quot;&gt;Useful links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/steveandriole/2019/10/23/software-rules-the-world---its-kingdom-is-growing/?sh=270459e57d28&quot;&gt;Software Rules the World – &amp;amp; Its Kingdom is Growing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tiempodev.com/blog/current-job-market-for-software-development-professionals/#:~:text=According%20to%20the%20US%20Bureau,all%20occupations%20is%20about%204%25.&quot;&gt;Current Job Market for Software Development Professionals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
        <category term="Thoughts" />
      

      
        <category term="Africa" />
      
        <category term="Senegal" />
      
        <category term="Tech Job" />
      
        <category term="Software development" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Software Rules the World – &amp;amp; Its Kingdom is Growing The “father of software quality” Watt S. Humphrey said 2 decades ago. Every business is a software business</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
</feed>
